Guide to the Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition Records, 1985-2017 AIS.2015.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition Records
1985-2017
2004-2011
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition
AIS.2015.03
5.17 Linear Feet (5 cartons, 1 Hollinger box, 2 oversize folders)
The records of the Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition are composed of textual and audiovisual documents about the group's activities to promote awareness of war and genocide in the Darfur region of Sudan. These records date from 2004-2017.
History
A non-profit organization affiliated with the Thomas Merton Center and Global Switchboard, Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition (PDEC) was founded in August 2004 by David Rosenberg, Molly Rush, Wanda Guthrie, and Sister Barbara Finch. The Coalition was an informal group with no known officers aside from Rosenberg, who was the Coordinator. According to its website, the PDEC's goal was to "mobilize public support for our aims and translate them to policy by organizing public events and generating media coverage." To further that mission, PDEC coordinated petition drives, marches, and informational installations intended to educate the public about the War in Darfur and resulting genocide of non-Arabic Darfuris in southwestern Sudan.
PDEC worked with several other organizations, including Save Darfur Coalition and local chapters of Students Taking Action Now: Darfur to pursue their shared mission. PDEC hosted several conferences on contemporary events in Sudan. These conferences brought together members of the Sudanese community in western Pennsylvania with policy experts, such as Jendayi E. Frazer and Scott Gration, to discuss past issues and present possible solutions to the genocide in Darfur. The group was represented in national rallies and marches through bus trips to New York City and Washington, DC. At one of the marches, PDEC members presented thousands of petition signatures to elected and appointed officials.
Beginning in 2007, PDEC began work on the Destroyed Villages Project. The project consisted of marches and installations of hundreds of signs, each listing the name of a Darfuri town or village destroyed by the Sudanese military or its allies. The ultimate presentation of the Project was at the 2009 G-20 Summit in Pittsburgh. After the creation of South Sudan in 2011, PDEC supported mission work in the new country and also worked to bring regional members of the Sudanese diaspora in contact with non-profit organizations and U.S. diplomats in a series of forums.
In the same year, Save Darfur Coalition merged into another organization and changed its mission to pursue an end to all genocides worldwide. PDEC continued its mission to bring awareness and support the needs of Sudanese diaspora members within the Western Pennsylvania region until 2017.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
Records are arranged chronologically within intellectually determined series. The intellectual arrangement is based upon Dr. Rosenberg's initial organizational scheme.
Those series are:
Series I. Administrative
Series II. Events
Series III. Informational Handouts
Series IV. Petitions
Series V. Research Materials
Series VI. News Clippings
Series VII. Proclamations
Series VIII. Media and Realia
Acquisiton Information
Gift of David Rosenberg, 2015. Additional materials were donated in 2017 by Dr. Rosenberg and in 2018 by Mary Dawn Edwards.
Related Material
Thomas Merton Center Records, 1962-2009, AIS.1982.19, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
David Rosenberg Papers, 1983-2007, AIS.2009.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scope and Content Notes
Records include a variety of textual and audiovisual documents which reflect the Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition's (PDEC) administrative practices, research practices, communications, and demonstrations. Included in this collection are meeting agendas, financial records, petitions, news clippings about the group's activities, and publications consulted by the PDEC.
Correspondence; Financial records; Petitions; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Social advocacy -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies, etc.; Protest movements; Human rights -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Associations, institutions, etc. -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Postcards; Pamphlets; Notes; Mailing lists; Digital images; Activists; Ethnic groups; Ethnic groups -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Genocide -- Sudan -- Darfur; Nonprofit organizations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Sudan -- History -- Darfur Conflict, 2003-; Color prints (Photographs); Photo CDs; Global Switchboard; Save Darfur Coalition; Rosenberg, David Lee; Thomas Merton Center (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition; Edwards, Mary Dawn; Students Taking Action Now: Darfur
- Administrative, 2004-2017; I.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administrative functions of the Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition, including but not limited to financial records, mailing lists, agendas and minutes, and correspondence.
  - Agendas, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agendas, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agendas, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agendas, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agendas, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agendas, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agendas, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Agendas, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Agendas, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Agendas, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Agendas, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Agendas, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Agendas, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Agendas, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, January - June 2005 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, July - December 2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, January - June 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, July - December 2006 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, January - June 2007 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, July - December 2007 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 2015-2017 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, drafts, 2004-2011 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Financial Records, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Financial Records, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Financial Records, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
  - Financial Records, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Financial Records, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Financial Records, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Financial Records, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Financial Records, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Financial Records, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Financial Records, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Financial Records, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Financial Records, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Financial Records, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Grants and Permits, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Grants and Permits, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Grants and Permits, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Grants and Permits, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Grants and Permits, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Grants and Permits, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Grants and Permits, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Operations, Mary Dawn's Files, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Operations, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Operations, Mary Dawn's Files, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Operations, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Operations, Mary Dawn's Files, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Operations, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Operations, CORO Fellow, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Operations, Mary Dawn's Files, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Operations, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Operations, Mary Dawn's Files, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Operations, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Operations, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Operations, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Operations, Memoir Outline, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Operations, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Operations, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Operations, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Operations, Mailing and Phone Lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Operations, Sign-In Sheets, 2004-2009 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Events, 2004-2017; II.
  This series contains records related to events held by Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition. Larger scale events have their own folders separate from general events.
  - Events, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Events, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Bus Trip, Rally to Save Darfur, Washington, DC, April 30, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
  - Bus Trip, Voices to Stop Genocide, New York, NY, September 17, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Divestment, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania General Assembly, 2006-2009 (Box 2, Folder 34-40)
  - Lobby Visits, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Events, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Destroyed Villages Project, 2007-2010 (Box 2, Folder 43-48)
  - Lunch with Ruth Messinger, February 21, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Torch Relay, October 8, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Events, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Divestment, Summer Olympics, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Events, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bus Trip, Inauguration, Washington, DC, January 20, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jerry Fowler visit, March 2009 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bus Trip, Save Darfur Memorial, Washington, DC, April 19, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - G-20 Demonstrations, September 2009 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Conference, The Way Forward in Darfur and South Sudan, March 2010 (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
  - Jendayi Frazer, "Choice for War or Peace in Sudan", November 16, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Events, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Events, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Events, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Events, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Events, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Forum, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Forum, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Forum, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Posters and Maps, 2006-2013; 2 folders (Map-case 32, Drawer 1)
- Informational Handouts, 2004-2014; III.
  This series contains handouts and fliers for event promotion and informational purposes.
  - "Information & Interesting Mailers", 2004-2006 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "Steps Toward Ending Darfur Genocide", 2006 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Support for Darfur Acct. Act", undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Save Darfur", 2007 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Take Action: Save Darfur (Bracelets)", ca. 2005 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Fact Sheet on Darfur (How It Began)", ca. 2005 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Darfur: A 21st Century Genocide", undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "PDEC Protest Sudan Govt @ U of Pittsburgh", May 2005 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Facts vs. Sudanese Embassy's Fictions", May 20, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Genocide in Sudan", 2005 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Background, September 2005 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "Darfur Fast", October 2005 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "Take Action Stop the Genocide", December 2005 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Mid-Atlantic States March and Rally, April 2007 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Five Years of a Genocide, October 2008 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - End the Genocide in Darfur with Your Voice, ca. 2009 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Proofs, ca. 2009 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Danger in Darfur Bus Trip, April 2009 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Pre G-20 Press Conference and Solemn Walk, September 2009 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - B'nai Mitzvah Project, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - March and Rally for Peace in Sudan, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Mystery Exhibit, Duquesne, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - 2 Years, 2 Sudans, April 2013 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Conflict in Sudan: Glossary of Terms, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Petitions, 2005-2014; IV.
  This series contains various petitions created by Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition and signed by community members.
  - "Sign In for Peace Rally, Submitted to President Bush", April 2005 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Signed Petitions, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Signed Petitions, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Overdue Notice, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Quotes from 2008-2009 Cards (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Signed Petitions, PA General Assembly Divestment, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Signed Petitions, PA General Assembly Divestment, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Save Darfur, blank, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Petition Cards, 2011-2012 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Letters to US Representatives Rothfus, Doyle, and Murphy, October 23, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Letters to Secretary H.R. Clinton, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Pittsburgh Petition, blank, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Pittsburgh Petition, signed, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 59)
- Research materials, 1985-2017; V.
  This series contains external publications and internal notes that were used by Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition in their communications and activities.
  - Argentina and Sudan, 2006-2009 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Saudi Arabia and Sudan, 2006-2009 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - In These Times, April 17-23, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2004-2006 (Box 3, Folder 63-70)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Report of the International Commission of Inquiry on Darfur to the United Nations Secretary General, January 25, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Darfuris in Israel, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, 2015-2016 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Background, History, and Legislation, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Research Articles, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Research Articles, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Research Articles, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 20-22)
  - Research Articles, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Research Articles, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Research Articles, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Research Articles, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Research Articles, 2011 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Research Articles, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Research Articles, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Research Articles, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Research Articles, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Research Articles, 2017 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- News clippings, 2004-2016; VI.
  This series contains news clippings related to events and other activities hosted or sponsored by Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition.
  - News Clippings, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - News Clippings, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - News Clippings, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - News Clippings, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - News Clippings, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - News Clippings, 2011 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Pitt Magazine, Spring 2011 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - News Clippings, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - News Clippings, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - News Clippings, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - News Clippings, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Proclamations, 2004-2014; VII.
  This series contains proclamations presented to the Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition.
  - Allegheny County Council, March 2008 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Allegheny County Council, March 2009 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, August 2004 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, September 2005 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, April 2006 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, October 2006 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, February 2008 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, May 2008 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, October 2008 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, September 2009 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, January 2011 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, May 2014 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Office of the Mayor (Pittsburgh), September 2005 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Save Darfur Coalition, April 2010 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - UNICEF Trick or Treat, April 2007 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Media and realia, 2005-2014; VIII.
  This series contains audiovisual media and realia that document the activities of the Pittsburgh Darfur Emergency Coalition.
  - Photographs, Abdel Bagi Kabeir Protest at University of Pittsburgh, May 21, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Photographs, Thumbnails for Destroyed Villages March, March 2009 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Photographs, "PDEC 2007 Images" (Box 5, Disc 1)
  - Video, Impact (WPXI-TV), 2008 (Box 5, Disc 2)
  - Audio, Lynn Cullen Show (WPTT-AM), February 15, 2008 (Box 5, Disc 3)
  - "Destroyed Villages Rally Poster PDF", April 2008 (Box 5, Disc 4)
  - Photographs, "PDEC Images As Shot, 5/18", 2008 (Box 5, Disc 5)
  - Video, "Time Code, Darfur Rally, 5-18-08" (Box 5, Disc 6)
  - Video, "PDEC - March/Rally, May 18, 2008" (Box 5, Disc 7)
  - Video, "May 18, 2008 March & Rally PDEC" (Box 5, Disc 8)
  - Photographs, "PDEC Villages Images - Unedited, C.M.U. Setup, March 9, 2009" (Box 5, Disc 9)
  - Photographs, "PDEC Villages Ex. Day 1 Images", March 2009 (Box 5, Disc 10)
  - Photographs, "PDEC Villages Exhibit Day 2 Images", March 2009 (Box 5, Disc 11)
  - Video, "PDEC Wash, DC 4-19-09 2 hrs" (Box 5, Disc 12)
  - Video, "PDEC Raw Footage 1 hr 12 min", September 14, 2009 (Box 5, Disc 13)
  - Video, "PDEC Sept 14, 2009, 83 min, No Chapters" (Box 5, Disc 14)
  - Photographs, "Pre G-20 Press Conference + Solemn Walk 9/14/09" (Box 5, Disc 15)
  - Video, "PDEC Jan 5, 2011 Raw Footage 1:22 min" (Box 5, Disc 16)
  - Photographs, "PDEC March + Rally for Peace in Sudan 1/5/11 (Chelsey Engel)" (Box 5, Disc 17)
  - Video, "PDEC Jan. 5, 2011 Peace In Sudan March Rally edits Pt. 1+2 15 min each" (Box 5, Disc 18)
  - Photographs, "PDEC Rally", January 5, 2011 (Box 5, Disc 19)
  - Photographs, "PDEC Diaspora Dinner, Chelsey Engel, 03/12/12" (Box 5, Disc 20)
  - "PDEC Website 11/27/12" (Box 5, Disc 21)
  - Photographs, "Duquesne Exhibit, PDEC, Chelsey Engel", October 2013 (Box 5, Disc 22)
  - Photographs, "PDEC 4/6/14 Chelsey Engel" (Box 5, Disc 23)
  - Photographs, "PDEC City Council 5/13/14" (Box 5, Disc 24)
  - "PDEC Website, 6/19/14" (Box 5, Disc 25)
  - Photographs, "PDEC May 2015" (Box 5, Disc 26)
  - Photographs, "PDEC 2018, Chelsey Engel" (Box 5, Disc 27)
  - Video, KDKA-TV News at 11, April 2, 2005 (Box 5, Video 1)
  - Video, "May 21, 2005, KDKA-TV News 6:00pm, 11:00pm" (Box 5, Video 2)
  - Video, "Darfur 5-18-08 #1" (Box 5, Video 3)
  - Video, "Darfur 5-18-08 #2" (Box 5, Video 4)
  - Video, "PDEC Long Edit 58:06", September 2, 2008 (Box 5, Video 5)
  - Video, "PDEC Save Darfur Highlights", September 2, 2008 (Box 5, Video 6)
  - Video, "Darfur 1 DC 4-19-09" (Box 5, Video 7)
  - Video, "Darfur 2 DC 4-19-09" (Box 5, Video 8)
  - Video, "9-14-09 #1" (Box 5, Video 9)
  - Video, "Darfur Summit 3-19-10" (Box 5, Video 10)
  - Green Ribbon Pin (Box 6)
  - Peacekeepers Now Baseball Cap (Box 6)
  - Save Darfur Painter's Cap (Box 6)
  - Wristbands (Box 6)